Guide to the Otto A. Bessey Papers 1928-1985
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Otto A. Bessey papers
1928-1985
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 242
Bessey, Otto A. (Otto Arthur), 1904-1984
7.0 linear feet
This collection contains correspondence, diplomas, and other personal materials of Otto A. Bessey, an administrator and scientist specializing in nutrition, toxicology, and biochemistry. Bessey (1904-1996) was considered a founding member of the scientific staff of the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences.
Biographical Note
Otto Arthur Bessey was born in Niotaze, Kansas on October 7, 1904; the oldest of Arthur and Belle Bessey's three children. The Bessey family moved from Kansas to Kalispell, Montana in the 1910s.
Otto Bessey graduated from the University of Montana with a degree in chemistry in 1928. He married Kathryn L. Munro on September 10, 1929 in Kalispell, Montana (the marriage would end in divorce). They would have two sons, Otto Alonzo and Roger. Bessey received his Ph.D. in biochemistry from the University of Pittsburg in 1932. Bessey became a skilled administrator and scientist specializing in nutrition, toxicology, and biochemistry He held research and teaching positions at Columbia University, Harvard Medical School, University of Illinois, the University of Texas Medical School, and the Public Health Research Institute of the City of New York. He also held prominent positions with the Environmental Protection Division at the U.S. Army Natick Laboratory, the Public Health Service, and the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS). While at the NIEHS, he was responsible for the dissemination of monies for research and training; Bessey was considered a founding member of the organization's scientific staff. Dr. Bessey retired in 1974.
Otto Bessey passed away on February 6, 1984 in Kensington, Maryland from a stroke. His second wife, Alice Louise Riedinger, passed away on December 15, 1996.
The collection contains Otto Bessey's correspondence, diplomas, and other personal materials. There are items relating to his career including official reports from organizations he worked for, classroom lectures, professional correspondence, certificates, and research materials. Also included are drafts and notes for articles and speeches by Bessey on various topics. The collection also contains photographs and several artifacts including an award for service from the US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.
This collection has been organized into nine series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1934-1984, 2.0 linear feet
Series II: Personal, 1924-1985, 1.1 linear feet
Series III: Reports, 1941-1951, 0.1 linear feet
Series IV: Research, 1938-1976, 2.4 linear feet
Series V: Writings, 1933-1976, 0.4 linear feet
Series VI: Teaching, 1940-1977, 0.4 linear feet
Series VII: Clippings, 1933-1979, 0.1 linear feet
Series VIII: Photographs, 1932-1977, 0.1 linear feet
Series IX: Memorabilia, 1955-1975, 0.4 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The collection was in possession of the creator until his death in 1984 and passed to his family until its donation to Archives and Special Collections in 1997.
No additions to this collection are expected.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bessey, Otto A. (Otto Arthur), 1904-1984--Archives
National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences
Biochemistry--Study and teaching; Environmental health; Nutrition; Public health
Medicine and Health; Science
Scientists--United States
- Correspondence, 1934-1984; Series I; 2.0 linear feet
  This series includes correspondence between Otto Bessey and different individuals and organizations, organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - American Association of Clinical Chemists, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1952-1955 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Otto Gaebler, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Otto Gaebler, 1953 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Otto Gaebler, 1954 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Otto Gaebler, 1955 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Joseph Harrison, 1949-1983 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, W. M. Sperry, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - American Board of Clinical Chemistry, Publicity, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - American Board of Nutrition, 1961-1976 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - American Chemical Society, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - American Chemical Society, 1961 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - American Chemical Society, Eli Lily Award, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - American Institute of Nutrition,Osborne and Mendel Award, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - American Institute of Nutrition, Mead Johnson Award, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - American Institute of Nutrition, Mead Johnson Award, 1980 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Analytical Biochemistry, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - "A" Miscellaneous, 1974-1981 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Otto Alonzo Bessey, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Roger Bessey, 1953-1962 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Sara R. Bock, 1948 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - "B" Miscellaneous, 1949-1976 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Children's Hospital, B6 Deficiency, 1958 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Columbia University, 1944-1974 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - "C" Miscellaneous, 1957-1980 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Department of Environmental Health, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - E. Ralph Dusek, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - "D" Miscellaneous, 1978 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - "E" Miscellaneous, 1950-1962 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - "F" Miscellaneous, 1940, 1974 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Greylock Center, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - "G" Miscellaneous, 1970 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Harvard University, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - "H" Miscellaneous, 1961-1974 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - International Commission on Nomenclature, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - International Nutrition Conference, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - "I" Miscellaneous, 1961-1983 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - John B. Pierce Foundation, 1974-1983 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - "J" Miscellaneous, 1950-1980 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - "K" Miscellaneous, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - "L" Miscellaneous, 1957-1983 (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Mount Sinai School of Medicine, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 2/29)
  - "M" Miscellaneous, 1956-1974 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - National Board of Medical Examiners, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - National Cancer Institute, Cancer Symposium, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - National Vitamin Foundation, Scientific Advisory Committee, 1946 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - National Vitamin Foundation, Symposium on Nutrition, 1949 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - New York University Medical Center, 1945-1976 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Nutrition Foundation, Nutritional Surveys, 1946-1954 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - "N" Miscellaneous, 1946-1980 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Obituary and Sympathy re: Otto Bessey, 1984 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - "O" Miscellaneous, 1947-1975 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Public Health Institute, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - "P" Miscellaneous, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - "R" Miscellaneous, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - "S" Miscellaneous, 1957-1974 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - M. Tishler, 1949-1956 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - "T" Miscellaneous, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - University of Illinois, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - University of Illinois, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - University of Montana, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - University of Montana, 1959-1976 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - University of Southern California, School of Medicine, 1983 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - University of Texas, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - University of Texas, 1934-1956 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - University of Texas, 1948-1977 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - United States Departments, 1952-1983 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - "U" Miscellaneous, 1956-1981 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Visitors, 1943-1951 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - "V" Miscellaneous, 1956-1974 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - S. B. Wolbach, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - S. B. Wolbach, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - S. B. Wolbach, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - "W" Miscellaneous, 1956-1975 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - "Y" Miscellaneous, 1950-1978 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Unidentified, 1955-1980 (Box-folder 4/15)
- Personal, 1924-1985; Series II; 2.0 linear feet
  This series includes items related to Otto Bessey's personal life and education, it is organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Legal Documents, American Board of Clinical Chemistry, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Appointments, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Appointments, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Appointments, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1928-1974 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Biographical, 1975 and undated (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Employment and Honors, 1947-1975 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Employment and Honors, 1956-1975 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Medical Records and Death Certificate, 1951-1984 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Passports and Vaccination Records, 1950-1975 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - State University of Montana Graduation Certificate and Misc., 1928 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1933-1973 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Curriculum Vitae II, 1924-1985 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Personal, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Personal, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 6/3)
- Reports, 1941-1951; Series III; 0.1 linear feet
  This series contains various reports from organizations related to Otto Bessey's work, organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Department of Chemistry, University of Illinois, 1951 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Annual Report of Public Health, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Annual Report of Public Health, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Annual Report of Public Health, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Nutrition and Physiology, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Subcommittee on Vitamin Nomenclature, 1951 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Survey of Medical Education, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 6/10)
- Research, 1938-1976; Series IV; 2.4 linear feet
  This series contains Otto Bessey's research files, organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Academic Institutions, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Application of Probability Theory, 1959 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Asbestos, undated (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Ascorbic Acid Fortification of Citrus Fruit Concentrates, 1944 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Ascorbic Acid, Solomon and Bessey, 1954 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - B6, Rats (Book 114), 1954 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - B6 and Xanthurenic Acid, Babies (Book 112), 1953-1954 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Biochemistry-Metabolic Antagonists, 1955 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Blood, Vitamin C (Book VII), 1938 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Candidates for Review Groups, undated (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Consultant Files, 1949-1976 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Dental Medicine, 1948 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Desulfhydrase (Book 115), 1954 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Environmental Health and Problem Area, 1977 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Graphs, undated (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Guinea Pig Collagen, 1936 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Harvard Thiamin Studies, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Health Consequences of Environmental Controls, 1974 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Health Effects of Coal and Oil Shale, 1975 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Health Notes, 1978 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Microbiological Assay (Book 11), 1943-1944 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Microbiological Assay, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Mostly Phosphatase #3, 1942 (Box-folder 8/10)
  - Notes on Mount Sinai, 1974 (Box-folder 8/11)
  - Mutagenesis, 1973 (Box-folder 8/12)
  - NAS Symposium Statistics, 1974 (Box-folder 8/13)
  - New York State Nutritional Survey, 1946 (Box-folder 8/14)
  - New York State Survey, Analysis Date-Hemoglobin, 1946 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - New York State Survey, Graphs and Summery Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - New York State Survey, Ptase, 1946 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - New York State Survey, Serum Protein, 1946 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - New York State Survey, Riboflavin, 1946 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Notes, Nutrition, undated (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Notes, PCBs, 1971 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Notes, Phthalic Acid Ester Conference, 1972 (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Problems and Remarks, undated (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Problems and Things to Do, undated (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Reading Lists, 1952 (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Planning, 1975 (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Riboflavin, undated (Box-folder 9/13)
  - Riboflavin (Book 111), 1953 (Box-folder 9/14)
  - Riboflavin Study, 1953 (Box-folder 9/15)
  - Serum Proteins, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Taurine Breast Secretions, Book 117, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Technical Notes, 1961 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - General Information, Travel Programs, 1964 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Travel Notes, 1964 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Travel Notes, Yugoslavia, 1966 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Travel Notes, Poland, 1966 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Travel Notes, Egypt Seminar, 1966 (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Russian Visit Plan, 1972 (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Baitelle Conference Travel, 1974 (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Plastic Conference, 1974 (Box-folder 10/11)
  - Vitamin B Tests, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 10/12)
  - Vitamins and Miscellany (Book 110), 1953 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Xanthuranic Acid and Pyridoxine, Babies Breast Milk, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 11/2)
- Writings, 1933-1976; Series V; 0.4 linear feet
  This series contains articles and addresses written by Otto Bessey, organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Charter Day, UM, 1954 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - University of Illinois, Chicago, 1971 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Journal Articles, 1933-1942 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Journal Articles, 1943-1976 (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Journal Articles, 1933-1942 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Journal Articles, 1943-1976 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Riboflavin and Thiamine in persons receiving Atabrine, 1957 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Vitamin B6 Intake and Infantile Convulsions, 1954 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Vitamin B6 Intake and Infantile Convulsions, 1954 (Box-folder 12/5)
- Teaching, 1940-1977; Series VI; 0.4 linear feet
  This series contains materials from Otto Bessey's teaching career, organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Exams, 1942, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Exams, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Exams, 1953--1955 (Box-folder 12/8)
  - Exams, undated (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 12/10)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/2)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Lectures, Biochemistry, University of Illinois, undated (Box-folder 13/6)
  - Lectures, Harvard, 1940 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - Lectures, Harvard, 1955 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - Lectures, University of Illinois, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 13/9)
  - Lectures, B6 Requirements in Infants, 1954 (Box-folder 13/10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977, undated (Box-folder 13/11)
- Clippings, 1933-1979; Series VII; 0.1 linear feet
  This series contains published articles about Otto Bessey and an article on chemical nomenclature that related to his profession.
  - Chemical Nomenclature, 1954-1956 (Box-folder 13/12)
  - University of Montana, 1933, 1954 (Box-folder 13/13)
  - Who's Who, 1947-1961 (Box-folder 13/14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-1979 (Box-folder 13/15)
- Photographs, 1932-1977; Series VIII; 0.1 linear feet
  This series contains photographs of Otto Bessey and some of his colleagues.
  - Photographs, 1928-1972 (Box-folder 13/16)
  - Photographs, 1940-1977 (Box-folder 13/17)
- Memorabilia, 1955-1975; Series VIII; 0.2 linear feet
  This series contains thermometers, an award for service from the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, and various certificates.
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box-folder 14/1)